[Music]
in a previous video
we saw a visual proof of this formula
for the sum of the first
n positive squares
what happens if we instead consider the
alternating sum
of squares is there a nice formula now
let's take a look
a square array with side length n
represents the value n squared
removing the upper n minus 1 by n minus
1 square
corresponds to subtracting n minus 1
squared
we can add back an n minus 2 by n minus
2 square and then
remove the upper right n minus 3 by n
minus 3 square
we can continue this process alternating
between adding a square back
and removing the next square array until
eventually
we add or subtract the two by two square
and then subtract or add back the one by
one square
the resulting l shaped gnomons can then
be squished together
to produce a triangular array with base
n
which has t n squares where t
n is the nth triangular number therefore
the alternating sum of the first
n squares is the nth triangular number
you